Okay, today's דף *daf*, welcome back after our תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*
break.
Today's דף *daf* is ס"ד *Samech Dalet*, a new פרק perek *perek*,
ninth פרק *perek*, and we actually move from a discussion of the
scope of the נדר Neder, *neder*, what certain words mean, what the
scope of time is, and so on—this isn't working right now—to the
question of התרת נדרים Hatarat Nedarim, *Hatarat Nedarim*, which is, you know,
it's interesting the way the משניות *mishnayot* sometimes move back and forth
between those two scenes, right? So we had a little התרת נדרים
hatarat nedarim *Hatarat Nedarim* before, we had a category of four נדרים
Nedarim. *nedarim* which are נדרי טעות ta'ut, *Nidrei Ta'ut* essentially, right? Remember
the category of the four נדרים Nedarim *nedarim* when it wasn't your
intention and you didn't really mean it and so on, which serves
as the conceptual basis for התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim *Hatarat Nedarim*. So
now we once again revisit the issue of התרת נדרים nedarim *Hatarat
Nedarim*. So let's take a look. Already a question, let's read the
משנה mishnah *mishna* first. What? Yes.
Did you have anything to say in terms of it being unusual
that there's a משנה mishna *mishna* and like no גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
at all?
No, I mean, well, you mean what we did yesterday? Well, what
was on the, you know, was the day two days ago which
was yesterday's דף *daf*. Well no, because if, you know, to some
degree that's the printer's decision because he could have put the whole
thing as a משנה mishna, *mishna* and had the little piece of
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* on the first part of the משנה mishna *mishna*,
you know? Sometimes the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't comment on the entire,
you know, on major sections of a משנה mishna *mishna*. So it
is strange from the, you know, the printer's decision, you know, the
publisher's decision, you know, to put it here without a גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* following it, but you could imagine that it could have put
the whole משנה Mishna, *mishna*, you know, and then the little גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that went on the first part of the משנה Mishna.
*mishna*, but yeah, because we do expect the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to
follow a משנה *mishna*. Okay, let's look now at the beginning of
the next פרק *perek*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer Omer*,
top of ס"ד *Samech Dalet*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says,
פותחין לאדם Potchin LeAdam? בכבוד אביו ואמו b'kavod aviv v'imo. *potchin l'adam
b'kvod aviv v'imo*. You open up, you know, for a נדר Neder.
*neder*, you open up with the issue of the honor of the
mother and the father. What does that mean? Means that you tell
somebody: had you known how this vow would have impacted your mother
and father, would you have taken the vow? חכמים Hachamim אוסרין *Chachamim
Ossrin*, and the Rabbis forbid it because they feel that then it'll
basically just be a license for everybody to get out of all
vows.
Now, what do you exactly say to the person? So if you
look at the ר"ן Ran, *Ran*, the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says, שאומרין
לו *she-omrin lo*, you say to him, אילו ilu היית יודע yodeia
שמבזין אביך ואמך על דתקע בנדרים *ilu hayita yode'a she-mevazin avicha v'imecha
al de-taka b'nedarim*, if you would have known that people will, you
know, disgrace your mother and father, will say bad things about your
mother and father because of you, וכדאמרינן דקרו לרשיעא בר צדיקא, רשיעא
בר רשיעא *u-k'de-amrinan d'karu l'rashia bar tzadika, rashia bar rashia*, that people
call wicked people the children of righteous people, they still call them
wicked the son of wicked because they reflect on the doings of
the child reflects on the parents. So people will think poorly of
you and then they'll think poorly and they'll say bad things about
your parents. So had you known how your deeds would have led
to what people say about your parents, would you have taken the
vow? כלום היית נודר noder. *klum hayita noder*? So that's one thing,
that it'll lead to people saying bad things about your parents. לשון
אחר *lashon acher*, another way of saying this is, שאמרת מהם שאף
הם מזלזלין בנדרים *she-amarta me-hem she-af hem mezalzelin b'nedarim*, which seems to
me to be just another version of the above, meaning what you
do reflects on them, so they'll say, "Oh yeah, of course this
is what you're doing because you must have learned it from your
parents." So again, two ways of saying that they'll think poorly of
your parents. Right, so רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says something a little different.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, שאומרין לו *she-omrin lo*, you say to him,
אילו ilu היית יודע yodeia שאומרים על אביך *ilu hayita yode'a she-omrim
al avicha* אוי לו לאב שגידל בן רשע כזה שפרוץ בנדרים שכן
רשעים דרכם לנדור *oy lo l'av she-gidal ben rasha kazeh she-parutz b'nedarim
she-ken resha'im darkam lindor*. So not exactly they'll say bad things about
your father that it'll reflect poorly on their character or on their
child rearing, but that, you know, people will sort of say, "Oy,"
you know, to your parents, "Oy, you must feel terrible that you
have such a wicked son." Okay, and so who wants people to
be saying bad things about you to your parents? So it's not
exactly כבוד Kavod, אביך ואמך *kvod avicha v'imecha*, you know, in the
same way, but it's like if you would have known how, you
know, how this is going to get back to your parents and
it'll cause them anguish, you know, to hear about this. Now of
course it's very interesting because
because one wonders, you know, how the נדרים nedarim, *nedarim* were clearly
quite proliferate, you know, and as we read, you know, it occurs
all the time. "Oh, I'm not going to come to your house
for a meal. Oh well, a נדר Neder? *neder*, all of my
things are אסור assur *assur* to you unless you come to my
house for," I mean, it was happening right and left, you know?
So it seems that חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* are also trying, maybe that's
one reason not to be פותח poteach *poteach*, because it's a little
bit, it's a little, you know, it's a little like maybe חז"ל
*Chazal*'s aspirational that people would think this way about people that took
vows and it's not really true, it doesn't really resonate that people
really, you know, that this really and genuinely would reflect poorly on
the parents, so that might be one reason. reason actually, although that's
not what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara seems to treat
it as if no, it really will look bad on your parents,
but again, one wonders if חז״ל Hazal are reading what, the way
they would like to see society responding to vows, you know, reading
that into how society is actually responding, because it does not seem
like as broadly society that people had much of a problem with
this. Yes.
Yeah, I mean, they're not saying that your parents are actually saying
anything about the נדר, Neder, right? So people are saying to your
parents, it's like, you know, oh, did you- you know what I'm
saying? I mean, they could have said like, oh, you know, your
parents might have really disapproved about this. And they're not saying that.
That's a good point too.
Let's say his parents actually liked that he made this נדר. Neder
Right, well- He's always had a problem with wine, right?
Thank God. Well, it's always better in terms of the- that's a
good point, but you know, but then maybe that's
the- why it's a powerful פתח. Petach. But if it's about how
people think about it, then it doesn't matter whether your parents themselves
are okay with it. By the way, תוספות Tosafot actually says a
variation of the רש״י Rashi version. Not exactly that they'll say bad
things about your parents, more they'll say bad things about you to
your parents. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. He says, רבי אלעזר אומר פותחין
לאדם בכבוד אביו ואמו, Rabbi Elazar Omer Potchin LeAdam Bichvod Aviv V'Imo,
כלומר אילו היית יודע שאומרים עליך לאביך ולאמך ראיתם בנכם קל בנדרים
ויתביישו. Klomar Ilu Hayita Yodeia Sheomrim Alecha LeAvicha UL'Imcha Reitem Binchem Kal
B'Nedarim V'Yitbaishu.
People will say, have you seen what your son is doing? And
they'll be embarrassed as a result. So that works a little bit
more with the כבוד, kvod but again, not that they'll think poorly
about your parents, but it'll get back to your parents and it'll
be anguish to them. Okay, and what's the context of פותחין potchin
לאדם?
l'adam Is this at the moment when the guys are about to
make the נדר?
Neder, No,
no, no, no. He made a נדר, Neder he comes to the
בית דין, Beit Din, we're trying to find a way to get
out of it. So we're trying to find a way to say
to him, like, how had you- the classical way a נדר Neder
works, right, is through a פתח. Petach. Had I thought at the
time I took the vow about A, B, and C, I never
would have taken the vow. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says you
have a standard question you can ask somebody. Had you thought about
how this would have led to people saying bad things about your
parents, or how it would have gotten back to your parents and
it would have embarrassed them, or all these types of things, would
you have? Right.
So פתח Petach is always a technical term in this.
Yeah,
yeah, exactly. Dov, do you have another question?
Yeah, it seems to me it's- it addresses one of the what
always seemed to me like the key weaknesses of this idea of
התרת נדרים, nedarim which is, when you made a נדר, Neder you
were probably thinking about how it would affect you. Like, to say
that, oh, I didn't know how much I would really want to
take it back, that's
a
little
specious because you were thinking about yourself.
But when you involve the third party, it gives it a whole
different thing like, yeah, you probably weren't thinking about other people.
That's an excellent point. You're right, because a נדר Neder is- I
mean, there's the נדר Neder. that involves two people, but still, you
know, you're trying to get me to do something and I say
something about you, but still that's very much just thinking about the
two of us, right? It's very self-centered in that way. That's an
excellent point. And this is actually broadening it. So we have to
figure out why the חכמים Hachamim say you don't do that.
Okay, we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי צדוק, Amar Rabbi
Tzadok, and רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok already gives an indication why the
חכמים Chachamim? would reject this approach. עד שפותחין לו בכבוד אביו ואמו,
Ad ShePotchin Lo BiChvod Aviv V'Imo, if you're already prepared to talk
about the impact on the parents, יפתחו לו בכבוד
המקום. Yiftichu Lo BiChvod HaMakom. Talk about the honor to God. Remember,
we sort of have taken this general approach that it's considered to
be, you know, not good to take vows. The גמרא Gemara. before
had very harsh terms, right? Anybody who takes a נדר neder is
ראוי roy to be like pierced with a sword. So the גמרא
Gemara said that you're not פותח פתח poteach a petach that way
because that just scares everybody into saying, oh yeah, if I realized
that I never would have taken it, and then you don't get
an honest response. But even if you're not that harsh, you can
still be פותח בכבוד המקום. poteach biChvod HaMakom. Now, what's בכבוד המקום?
biChvod HaMakom? Is it this idea that we said that כל הנודר
כאילו בנה במה, Kol HaNozer K'Ilu Bana Bama, that it's basically not
a good thing? Or is there something else about that that's going
on? If you take a look at the ר״ן, Ran, he quotes
a- בכבוד המקום, biChvod HaMakom,
he says דהאמינה בספרי, DeHamina BeSifrei, the line starts שהוא, SheHu, it's
about ten lines down in the narrow lines, שהוא כנודר במלך עצמו,
SheHu KeNozer BeMelech Atzmo, כלומר היית נודר. Klomar Hayita Nozer. That somehow
there's an interesting ספרי Sifrei that distinguishes between כנודר בחיי המלך Nozer
BeChayei HaMelech as opposed to כנודר במלך עצמו, Nozer BeMelech Atzmo, and
somehow brings God into the world of נדרים. nedarim Now, it's not
exactly clear what that's getting at, especially because at most, right, God
is very front and center by a שבועה, Shvuah, right? A שבועה
Shvuah is with שם השם, Shem Hashem, and even without שם השם,
Shem Hashem, we assume for something to be a שבועה Shvuah you
need sort of like a יד yad to God's name, right? לא
ינקה השם את אשר ישא שמו לשוא. Lo Yenakeh Hashem Et Asher
Yisa Shemo Lashav. You swear in the name of God. A נדר
neder. is about not God directly, it's about the status of an
object. Even if you say קונם, konam, it's drawing on your power
to make something into a קרבן, korban, to maybe implicitly dedicate something
to God, but it's not so much about like somehow God's front
and center and God's honor is being violated when I violate a
נדר. neder So it is interesting that the ר״ן Ran brings that
idea down, and again, not exactly clear what the logic of that,
but I wanted to show you it because it seems like a
little bit of a crossover between שבועה Shvuah and נדרים nedarim, to
bring it like, you know, to God. make a נדר neder or
somehow about God's honor.
So it's more simple to just understand that the כבוד המקום k'vod
hamakom here is that you're not supposed to make נדרים nedarim that
you know, if you take a look at רש"י,
רש"י says, אף שכנגד הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה שנודר ורשע הוא לשמים.
af she'keneged Hakadosh Baruch Hu oseh shenoder v'rasha hu lashamayim. So that's
like you're not supposed to take vows. Okay, and again sort of
reflecting the rabbi's attitude, right? The rabbi's attitude is vows reflect poorly
on your parents, vows are an offense to God, right? Again, not
very much the common perception. Anyway, he says, if you're going to
bring in parents, you might as well bring in God. Okay, so
bring in God, why not? So then he says, אם כן אין
נדרים. im kein ein nedarim.
So then you can, there will be no vows because that's always
true. Anytime somebody takes a vow, if it's considered to be like
not religiously appropriate, you're not supposed to take vows, right? So then
everybody will always say, oh, I didn't mean it, and everybody will
get out of it. Okay, that's no, that's part of רבי צדוק.
Rabbi Tzadok. רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok is like a little reductio ad
absurdum, right? If you're going to bring in parents, you might as
well bring in God. And if you bring in God, then there
will never be a נדר. neder So of course you cannot do
this. Now the question is, well, why not? Maybe it's true. Maybe
if somebody had stopped to think about it, they wouldn't have done
it, and maybe there will be a general פתח. petach. So what
would be so bad? Okay, so we will take a look at,
what?
Everybody has parents.
Everybody has parents. Well, that's his point. Okay, so what's so bad?
אי נמי, ei nami, if we don't like vows and we want
to try to sort of stop people from doing it so much
and it genuinely is true that if people had thought it through
they wouldn't have done it, so then why not be פותח poteach
with parents? Why not be פותח poteiach with God? Okay, and the
גמרא Gemara is basically going to say about this, because then you're
not going to get an honest response. I mean, you could have
two answers. You could say that's true, actually, that would work. But
then, if we give a פתח petach that works for everybody at
all times, right? So then it has the opposite effect. Meaning on
the one hand, it means that people get out of their vows
and we have fewer vows in the world and that's maybe a
good thing. On the other hand, it makes people treat vows very
trivially. Oh yeah, big deal, just say I wasn't thinking about God,
wasn't thinking about my parents, right? It's too easy. So there's more
like a public policy reason why we don't want to give this
פתח, petach, right? We want to in a way make it easy
enough to get out of vows because we don't like all those
vows around and we want to encourage people to get to get
out of them and undo them and so on. And on the
other hand, we don't want to so trivialize it that actually it
means that people take vows left and right because they just feel
it's so easy to get out of and it doesn't mean anything.
So there could be like that public policy reason. The גמרא Gemara
is going to say a reason that sounds a little bit more
like, because then you're not going to get an honest answer. You're
going to scare people. If you say to somebody, do you know
how much your parents would be embarrassed if they found out about
this? Do you know how much this is like an act of
רשעות rishut to God? So who's going to want to say, yeah,
even though I knew that, I would have taken my vow? Okay?
So it's just too, you know, you're raising the stakes too high
and people are going to say they wouldn't have done it and
you're not going to get an honest answer. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to focus on.
Do you read רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok as an explication of the
חכמים?
Chachamim Yes, as a type of a showing why they're right because
it's reductio ad absurdum, you know?
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, ומודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר
בדבר שבינו לבין אביו ואמו שפותחין לו בכבוד אביו ואמו. umodim Chachamim
l'Rabbi Eliezer bidvar shebeino l'vein aviv v'imo shepotchin lo b'khvod aviv v'imo.
If it would have impacted the parents, like it was a vow
not to get benefit from the parents or not to give benefit
to the parents, then clearly you could bring in the parents, right?
You know, did you really think through how this would impact your
relationship with your parents? Okay, and so on, then you can obviously
bring it in. ועוד אמר רבי אליעזר, ve'od amar Rabbi Eliezer, so
that was one thing, that you always open up with the parents.
Then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, פותחין בנולד. potchin benolad. Now this
is even a bigger חידוש. chiddush. You can open up with something
that is newly born. You could say something that the person had
no right to expect at the time of the vow and then
it occurred after the vow. You could have said to them, had
you realized that this would have occurred, I'm saying נדר neder, that
I'll never get any benefit, you know, everything that Michael has is
אסור assur to me. And then tomorrow Michael wins the Mega Millions.
Okay, well, had I realized that, I never would have taken that
vow, right? That's נולד. nolad. Because if the logic of a פתח
petach is we're going to say that you didn't think it through
and, you know, if we really got deep down to what you
would have wanted to, what you really, you know, would have been
thinking had you thought it all through, then you wouldn't have taken
it and therefore it was a טעות, ta'ut, it was an error
because you were just, you know, you weren't really totally sort of
processing all of the issues. So in this case, if we go
back to how I felt yesterday, I never would have imagined he
would have won the Mega Millions, right? So yes, even if I
had thought through all of the issues, I would have taken the
vow because there was no reason for me to have imagined that
that would have happened in the future. So that's the problem with
נולד. nolad. And nevertheless, רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer says it doesn't matter,
we're still willing to say, had you realized that this would have
happened in the future, would you have done it? And if you
say no, that's a way to get you out of it. פותחין
בנולד. potchin benolad. What? That Ferrari?
There you go, had the Ferrari,
you wouldn't have given me off. Picked out, exactly. Okay, וחכמים אוסרים
veChachamim osrim and the חכמים Chachamim say it's forbidden.
Now this is different, right? Because... The first thing might be more
of a policy issue, whereas this might be that it doesn't really
work, because who cares had you known something that you couldn't have
known at the time? That doesn't make it into a טעות, ta'os,
right? So this debate might be more of a principle debate than
a policy debate. כיצד, keitzad, what would be an example of this?
אמר amar קונם konam שאני she-ani נהנה neheneh לאיש l'ish פלוני. ploni.
A person takes a vow that he won't get any benefit from
a certain person. ונעשה v'na'asah סופר, sofer, and then the person became
the סופר sofer of the עיר. ir. Now the סופר sofer doesn't
just mean the guy that fixes the תפילין tefillin and the מזוזות,
mezuzot, it also means the person that writes out the legal documents
and he, right, he's the scribe of the city. Everybody needs his
services. How can I get a legal document done without going to
him?
או o שהיה she-haya משיא masia את et בנו, beno, the guy
was now marrying off his son, and now everybody is expected to
be invited to the party. Okay, so this is just a one-time
thing as opposed to סופר sofer which is ongoing. And like, had
I, you know, I didn't realize I was ever going to have
anything to do with him, I didn't realize he was about to
marry off a child and then invite everybody to the party. ואמר,
v'amar, and you said, אילו ilu הייתי hayiti יודע yodeia שהוא she-hu
נעשה na'asah סופר. sofer. Had you realized that he would have become
a
scribe? או o שהיה she-haya משיא masia את et בנו beno בקרוב
b'karov in the near future. לא lo הייתי hayiti נודר. noder, And
this guy said, had I known that—not had you—had I known that
I would not have taken a vow. So קונם konam לבית l'bayit
זה zeh שאני she-ani נכנס, nichnas, or somebody says קונם konam that
this house that I can't go into it. ונעשה v'na'asah בית הכנסת,
beis haknesses, and then the house got bought and it turned into
a שול. shul.
Oh that might be a good measure.
אמר amar אילו הייתי hayiti יודע שהוא she-hu נעשה na'asah בית beit
הכנסת. haknesset, Had I known the house would have been turned into
a שול, shul, לא lo הייתי hayiti נודר, I would not have
taken a vow. רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer מתיר matir וחכמים vachachamim אוסרים.
osrim. רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer says that the... now here the מתיר
matir and אוסרים osrim is not just going on פותחין potchin whether
we open for him, what the בית דין beis din. procedure is,
it also seems like whether the vow remains binding, right? רבי Rabbi
אליעזר Eliezer says אוסר oser meaning the... house is still forbidden, it
remains binding... I'm sorry, I'm sorry, רבי אליעזר מתיר, matir, he permits
it and presumably it becomes permissible. And the חכמים chachamim say it's
forbidden, presumably not just that the בית דין beis din can't do
it, but even בדיעבד bedieved it's a problem, right? Because this is
the issue. The first part seemed to be more of a policy
thing and בדיעבד bedieved the first thing might work, whereas this seems
more of a principle thing. That's not a legitimate basis for saying
that your vow wasn't binding. That was not something you could have
anticipated at the time, and at the time you were totally sincere
and might have anticipated, you know, all the things that you would
have normally expected, and this was something that you couldn't reasonably expect,
so it does not undermine the commitment, you know, the conviction behind
the vow and the sincerity of the vow.
What's the difference between the סופר sofer case and the בית beit
הכנסת haknesset. case?
What? And in what way?
Well, what's the difference?
Well, there isn't a difference.
These are all forms of נולד. nolad.
These are all, these are all examples.
But what's the first... wait, are you saying that the בית beis
הכנסת haknesset case is לכתחילה, l'chatchila, it's like you can't use that?
No, no, no, I meant as opposed to when I said the
policy vs. לכתחילה l'chatchila בדיעבד, bedieved, I was talking about the case
about כבוד אביו ואמו.
kvod aviv
v'imo
כבוד אביו ואמו kvod aviv v'imo seems to be more of a
policy issue whereas this seems to me more of a case of
even בדיעבד bedieved it doesn't work. Is it really a basis for
it? Now by the way, there is a difference between, you know,
a נולד nolad that you could have expected as opposed to a
נולד nolad that you did not have a good reason to expect,
right? So like if you say to somebody, I don't know, they
took a certain vow about
not... I don't know, not doing something and said, had you thought
through that when it would have come the summer and things would
have become so hot and whatever it would have been, like I'm
not going to go into that מרחץ, merchatz, and he says it
in the winter, right? Had you thought through that once it became
the summer and things become so hot and you would need to
clean up? Oh no, actually I wasn't thinking about the summer, I
was thinking about the winter because we were in the middle of
the winter, right? So that's not, like that is something in the
future, but you know it's something you could have thought about. Okay,
now you can say like the summer always comes. But if there's
other things that you could have imagined, right? You know, I don't
know, like had you realized that, you know, your kid would have
gotten into this university? And that's reasonably possible that he would have
gotten in, and I could have, I should have thought that that
was reasonably possible at the time I took the vow, it just
hadn't happened yet. So things that would have been reasonably possible that
you could have expected, right, that is everybody agrees you can. The
question is a נולד nolad that you did not have a good
reason to expect might have happened, that's what the debate is about.
Yes?
Why is this not a difficult reading on your part? What compels
you to interpret the words מתיר matir and אוסרים osrim differently in
the סיפא seifa than in the רישא? reisha?
So I'm, you're right. I mean, well I do think it's a
little bit different that the סיפא... seifa... so it's not about the
words and the משנה are compelling me, it's conceptually that there's a
big difference here, right, between the רישא reisha which seems to me
to be a policy, and also the difference
is that in the סיפא seifa פותחין לאדם is talking to the
בית דין, beis din right? Are you פותח poteiach, to the person?
That's the question about what should they do, not בדיעבד bedieved what
happens if they did it. By the time you get to the
end it says he said אילו הייתי hayiti יודע שהוא she-hu נעשה
na'asah סופר. sofer.
The guy is saying this and they're saying אוסרים. osrim.
So it's not the question about פותח, he already actually said it.
You could still say it means אוסרים osrim to go ahead and
מתיר matir on the basis of it. It could still be about
the בית דין. beis din, I understand. I'm reading more because I
just feel that there is this halachic difference, but there's no text
in the משנה that really compels me yet.
He could have been given that response in
response to their question about had you known. Right. But we still
have no insight as to what kind of פתח pesach the חכמים
chachamim would allow.
Well, the classic פתח pesach is just had you thought about things
that you could have expected or that you should have been thinking
about. Right, but they didn't give us concrete examples. But you know,
but one example is in the משנה, כבוד אביו ואמו kvod aviv
v'imo by something that impacts the parents. So if I said, right,
קונם konam I'm not going to, I don't know, קונם konam that
my car is forbidden to me.
אוסרו אצלו? osaro etzlo?
No, no, no. מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר בדבר שבינו לבין אביו ואמו.
modim chachamim l'Rebbi Eliezer b'davar shebeino l'vein aviv v'imo.
Right.
Something that impacts the parents the חכמים chachamim admit. So if you
basically say קונם konam my car is forbidden to me because I
want to start biking and I want to get into better health,
and then you said had you realized that you would have had
to take your parents, you know, your father shopping or to the
doctors, oh no, then whatever, that would be a פתח. pesach. Do
you want to say something? No, okay, yeah.
Wait, so doesn't it make a difference if he would have said,
let's say, קונם בית זה שאיני נהנה konam bayis zeh she'eini nehene
as opposed to נכנס, nichnas, and then it becomes a בית beis
הכנסת, haknesset you could say he can go in anyway because מצוות
לאו ליהנות ניתנו? mitzvos lav l'henos nitnu?
So that might be about what's considered הנאה, hana'ah, right, that gets
to your question before about, you know, do we always mean הנאה
hana'ah like or do we also mean any type of use even
if it's not הנאה hana'ah
like when קונם סוכה שאני נכנס konam succah she'ani nichnas etc.? Sometimes
we discuss that. Right, sometimes the קונם, konam, is it referring to
what's technically הנאה hana'ah or is it concerning all use? The other
question is about, you know, use that's not necessarily related to the
מצוה mitzvah itself, like if it's fine, you know, using it as
a מקום תפילה makom tfillah might not be considered a מצוה, mitzvah,
but using it because it's got a roof and it's raining outside.
Right. So anyway, but that's a good, that's an important thing to
bring about, which is we've been discussing, right, you know, that a
נדר neder, can subvert doing a מצוה mitzvah like if you say
קונם סוכה שאני יושב, konam succah she'ani yosheiv, you know, תפילין שאני
לובש tfillin she'ani loveish etc. What about מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו? mitzvos
lav l'henos nitnu? But that might be because we're not defining it
as הנאה. hana'ah. We're saying what you're אוסרing oser is the entering
in, you're not אוסרing oser in הנאה. hana'ah.
Right, but I'm saying, but let's
say you actually said הנאה. hana'ah. So that could be. Yes, that
could be. That might, that is correct.
Everyone would agree that you could then go into that, that could
be. Yes. But not necessarily if it's raining, you
just like want to go... Right, that's a whole debate about how
to understand מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. mitzvos lav l'henos nitnu. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara But it's correct, there's
nothing in the משנה that makes a proof whether it's the first
part, whether we're talking about policy or בדיעבד bedi'avad or any difference
between the first or the second, I'm just reflecting on my own
thoughts about this. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
מאי אין נדרים? mai ein nedarim? What does it mean when they
say back, 'Oh well, if we would allow this, then it would
never be vows, because we'll always just say, oh you know, this
is bad to God and then okay, so big deal, fine, what's
the problem?' So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אם כן אין נדרים ניתרים
יפה. im kein ein nedarim nitarim yafeh. That somehow means that we're
not going to be doing it right. In what way are we
not going to be doing it right? So here everybody pretty much
says that then people will say, if you bring God into the
equation, parents into the equation, then you're not going to get an
honest answer from me. Who's going to really say 'Yes, I would
have done it even had I been thinking about the fact that
it's not religiously ideal?' or 'How'd I even have been thinking about
my parents?' Right? You're not, people won't give you that answer. People
are going to say, you know, are going to claim they wouldn't
have done it because they don't want to be making such a,
you know, brazen type of a statement, and we'll מתיר matir the
נדר neder. even when we shouldn't. So for example, look at the
ר"ן, he says two lines down the wide lines: אין נדרים ניתרים
יפה. ein nedarim nitarim yafeh. שאפילו אם מתחילה לא היה נמנע מכבוד
המקום, she'afilu im mitechila lo haya nimna mikvod hamakom,
even if some guy would have taken the vow regardless of the
fact that, you know, and one imagines that this happens by the
way all the time, right, that the rabbis are saying it's not
a religiously good thing to do and the people are still taking
the vows. So nobody is being נמנע nimna because of God's honor.
Nevertheless, if he's standing in front of the בית דין beis din.
and the בית דין beis din. is saying to him, 'Would you
have done this had you realized what a big sin it was?'
Right? So he's going to say, לא יעיז פניו בכך לפני חכם
וישקר. lo ya'iz panav bekach lifnei chacham veyeshaker. He wouldn't have such
חוצפה chutzpah to say 'Yeah, I knew that you guys didn't like
me to do it, or people say it's not a good, you
know, religious thing and I did it anyway.' He won't say that.
He'll be וישקר, veyeshaker, he'll lie, ויאמר אילו הייתי יודע לא הייתי
נודר. veyomar ilu hayiti yodei'a lo hayiti noder. נמצא שאין נדרים ניתרים
יפה. nimtza she'ein nedarim nitarim yafeh. Okay.
So bringing parents or bringing God into the equation is going to
get you a dishonest answer, and that's why we don't do it.
Okay, again, I think it's possible to read the משנה like I
said, that it's really more of a policy point. You know, if
you create a פתח pesach that everybody can use and everybody can
get out of,
then it trivializes נדרים, nedarim, right? Maybe that doesn't sit with the
word אם כן אין נדרים. im kein ein nedarim. But you could
read it, אין נדרים ein nedarim are treated seriously, נדרים nedarim are
treated like they're not real, they're not serious, it undermines the seriousness.
Anyway, that's not the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it. אביי
Abaye is reading it that the problem with this, according to the
חכמים chachamim or according to, you know, is that you won't get
an honest answer.
Difference between כבוד אביו ואמו kavod aviv v'imo, versus כבוד המקום, kvod
hamakom, right?
Well, that could be. רבי אליעזר could agree that you don't open
up בכבוד אביו aviv ואמו. v'imo. Could be that he said by
כבוד אביו ואמו, kavod aviv v'imo, I mean כבוד המקום, kavod hamakom,
that point I can see, because you won't get an honest answer,
okay, but כבוד אביו ואמו, kavod aviv v'imo, I think you will
get an honest answer and I do want to open up with
it. ורבא אמר, V'Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, אם כן איני,
im kein eini, top of דף ס"ד ע"ב, daf samach-dalet amud bet,
אם כן אין נדרים נשאלין לחכם. im kein ein nedarim nishalin l'chacham.
Nobody will bother asking a חכם, chacham, and this maybe is more
closer to what I was saying about the policy point. People will
say, oh yeah, why bother going to a חכם, chacham, I know
the escape. Oh, had you thought about that God didn't like it?
Would you want to do? No, fine, מותר, mutar, okay. So had
you thought about your parents don't like it? It's such a blanket
thing that applies to every single נדר, neder, that people will just
say so I don't need to go to a חכם, chacham, I
can get myself out of it. And even if it's true that
they will be the exact same process with the חכם, chacham, you
need the procedure in order to מתיר matir the נדר, neder right?
There's a... the procedure is based on concept of טעות, ta'os, but
it wasn't really a טעות, ta'os, it's going... it's really a case
that you really wanted what you said, but we're saying had you
been thinking it through, and that's a process of התרת נדרים nedarim
which is done through a בית דין, beis din. which is done
through a חכם chacham and through a בית דין. beis din. So
even if the reason is genuine, if people feel it's just so
universal, they'll think they don't even need to go through the procedure
and therefore they'll just completely like everybody will just מתיר matir their
own נדר.
neder You allowed for that in the last פרק or the previous
one? About מתיר matir in cases where you can
you don't even need to go to a חכם? chacham? Yes. So
there are cases when you don't have to go to a חכם
chacham when, when it wasn't in the scope of your vow, like
you sort of said like, oh, you know, what was the case
about, what was the last case about, I'm not going to go
into, oh, unless you give me this thing, you know, you give
my son this thing, then, you know, my stuff is אסור assur
to you. And said, well, it's like I received it. But that's
because the condition is
met, right? The חידוש chiddush is that we consider it to be
that the condition is met. Or some or we consider it like
this wasn't included in the scope, right? This person is forbidden to
me because whatever, because right.
So when
it's not in the scope of your vow or the condition is
considered to have been met, or it's a, right, or it's a
genuine טעות, ta'os right? Remember going back to the four categories of
נדרים which are real טעות from the beginning, like you're just haggling
and you didn't really mean it or you really made a mistake.
Those things you don't need a חכם. chacham. But when the condition
when all the conditions are met, it's in the vow, you were
sincere and at the time, and now we're retroactively saying we're going
to sort of inspect what you said and get to the bottom
of it and see that deep down under the, you know, you
really wouldn't have meant it, that the process of התרת נדרים that
requires a בית דין. beis din, So even if the conditions really
are met, it doesn't get allowed, permitted until there's a בית דין.
beis din. So anyway, so that's what רבא Rava is saying. רבא
Rava is saying is, you know, you just have given such a
broad license that it's possible to get out of any vow, people
will just מתיר matir for themselves and not even bother going to
a בית דין.
Beis Din And you were saying the same thing, don't you think
that both אביי Abaye and רבא Rava and the ר"ן's explanation of
אביי Abaye what's at stake here is the integrity of the judicial
process and the status of the חכמים chachamim in
the בית beit דין, din's right?
Well,
certainly part of the policy, but I
could see it, yeah, that's a way of saying, yeah, no, I
hear that, yeah, that's definitely a way of saying that, yes.
And it goes to something, you know, beforehand we have a whole
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thing, right? Like the נשאל על הפרט nishal
al haperat thing, right?
where רבי עקיבא... Rabbi Akiva...
Well, that's
going to be the question about what are the types of things
that you might imagine might have been able to have happened. That's
what you mean by... Yeah, exactly. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, yeah, because this idea that you're not פותח בנולד
pote'ach banolad there are some cases in the גמרא Gemara that are
seem to be against it and the ראשונים Rishonim have to try
to fit that into that system. Okay, that no you could have
expected this and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says
like
this. תנן. Tnan. So we have this debate of אביי Abaye and
רבא. Rava.
ומודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר בדבר שבינו לבין אביו ואמו שפותחין לו בכבוד
אביו ואמו. U'modim chachamim l'Rabbi Eliezer b'davar shebeino l'vein aviv v'imo shepotchin
lo bichvod aviv v'imo. So at least the חכמים chachamim concede the
case when it's something that really affects the person's relationship with his
parents, you know, or the honor of the parents. בשלמא לאביי דאמר
אם כן אין נדרים ניתרים יפה. Bishlama l'Abaye d'amar im kein ein
nedarim nitarim yafeh. So according to אביי Abaye that says the concern
is is that people will basically lie and that's why the חכמים
Chachamim say we don't ask about כבוד אביו ואמו, we can understand
this exception. הכא כיון דאחציף ליה אחציף ליה. Hacha keivan d'achtzif lei
achtzif lei.
Here if the person had the חוצפה chutzpah to basically take a
vow that did impact his parents, right, let's say a more immediate
case, I gave an indirect case like my car is אסור assur
and I wasn't thinking of that I'd need to use it for
my parents, but let's say a person said oh you know my
property is אסור assur to my parents or my parents' property is
אסור to me. So he directly knows that his parents are involved
and he's still willing to go ahead
and to take the vow. So in that type of a case
where he knowingly takes a vow even though it impacts his parents,
we can expect that we'll get an honest response from him if
he shows up in בית beit דין. din And we said had
you really thought through how it was going to impact your parents,
would you have taken the vow? And he will probably say yes,
you know, he knew that it was going to impact his parents
and he took the vow, so we're not afraid that by raising
the parents' issues we're going to just get a lie, because this
guy was honest enough, brazen and honest enough to take the vow.
knowing how it would impact the parents. So it explains why the
חכמים Chachamim allowed us to raise the parents in this issue. Okay,
you could ask, "How's it going to do any good?" because then
he'll say, "Of course," you know, because then it's not it's not
going to serve as a פתח, pesach, but maybe there'll be ways
it would. אלא רבא, Ella Rava, דאמר, de'amar, אם כן, im kein,
אין נדרים נשאלים לחכם, ein nedarim nishalim l'chacham, once we start raising
the parent issue, then people are going to just figure out that
they can think they can מתיר matir their own נדר, right? So
how could we ever raise the parent issue? הכא Hacha מאי פותחין?
mai poschin? Why do you discuss parents? Then people say, "Oh, last
time I was in בית beis דין din, they asked me about
my parents," so you know, and they'll bring it in themselves. Now
there's an obvious answer. There they asked you about your parents because
the
נדר directly impacted the parents. You're not going to think that you
can use that as a blanket way to get out of נדרים,
right? So the גמרא Gemara says, basically what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמרי, Amri, you could say, כיון דכל נדרי לא סגי להו בלא
חכם, keivan dechol nidrei lo sagi lehu belo chacham, הכא נמי פותחין.
hacha nami poschin. Since all other נדרים you need a חכם, chacham,
and you don't get this, you know, this allowance in terms of,
you know, you don't have this feeling that you can always get
out of it, there's this blanket היתר, heter, just mention my parents,
it's like the magic, you know, get out of jail free card
etc., you know in all other cases, in this one case
because it directly impacted your parents, you know, there we brought them
in. So that's not going to undermine your sense that you have
to go to a חכם. chacham. This is a singular exception, it's
not a blanket get out of jail free card. Okay. So we
have this debate of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. רבא Rava says,
אביי Abaye says that the problem is is that you're going to
get a dishonest answer. And רבא Rava says, which to me seems
like just, you know, more, I don't know, for whatever reason רבא's
Rava's approach speaks to me more, that which is maybe because it's
the language of the משנה, like, "Oh, then we'll just always do
it." Right, we could always just mention God, we could always just
mention everybody. So the fact that you can always universally invoke it
undermines the weight and the seriousness of the נדרים, people would just,
you know, trivialize their own נדרים and get out of their, feel
they can get out of their own נדרים and won't go through
this serious process. Okay, so that's the issue about bringing in the
parents.
It's a double
negative: לא סגי להו דלא חכם. lo sagi lehu dela chacham.
Right. Okay. ועוד אמר רבי אלעזר פותחין בנולד. Ve'od amar Rabbi Elazar
poschin b'nolad. Now we get to the נולד nolad issue. So that
was using a universal פתח pesach and now we get to the
נולד nolad issue. So מאי טעמא דרבי אלעזר? mai ta'ama deRabbi Elazar?
What's the reason of רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar? Because you know, the
logic of the חכמים makes sense. If it wasn't something you could
have reasonably expected at the time, how can you use it to
speak to your frame of mind at the time? So the גמרא
says, דאמר קרא אמר רב חסדא דאמר קרא, de'amar kra amar Rav
Chisda de'amar kra, he gets it from a verse: כי מתו כל
האנשים המבקשים את נפשך. ki meisu kol ha'anashim ham'vakshim es nafshecha. This
is what God says to משה Moshe by going back to מצרים.
Mitzrayim. And if you remember the גמרא says, ויואל משה לשבת את
האיש, vayo'el Moshe lasheves es ha'ish, right,
ויואל vayo'el not just means משה Moshe desired, but from the word
of אלה alah of an of an oath, right, והשביע הכהן את
האשה בשבועת האלה, ve'hishbia hakohen es ha'isha bishvuas ha'alah, that משה Moshe
took an oath to יתרו Yisro that he would not go back.
So how is he going to get out of that oath? So
God is being מתיר matir the נדר because He's saying, "Oh, because
you only took the oath because there were people there that were
after your life. They've now died, so had you, you know, now
you can get out of the oath because had you been thinking
about the fact that they would have died then you would not
have taken that oath." Okay, so that's how he got out of
it.
Woah, let's play say something else. Yes.
That's like a huge pun on the סאטמר רב'ה's Satmar Rebbe's treatise...
Oh I was going to say that! It wasn't a pun, that's
why he called it that!
I know, I know.
Because his whole, because the סאטמר רב'ה's Satmar Rebbe's whole treatise about
against Zionism is about the גמרא about the שלוש שבועות shalosh shavuos
and that's the ויואל משה, Vayo'el Moshe, right, about the oath.
Yeah, and also the pun is a double pun, ויואל Vayo'el his
name is יואל Yoel Teitel...
Oh, is that right, right, right, right. יואל טייטלבוים. Yoel Teitelbaum.
There you go. Okay, that...
אילו לא באת Ilu lo basa to learn the entire מסכת masechet
just for this...
דיינו. Dayeinu. Exactly.
All right. So now the גמרא says like this. Okay, והא מיתה
דנולד הוא? ve'ha misa de'nolad hu? Death is something, you know, not
expected. That משה Moshe didn't expect them to die so suddenly or
whatever. Who knows, you know, maybe they would outlive him, he would
outlive them, you know, whatever. It's not like had you... so it
wasn't something that reasonably would have been expected, you know, would expect
that would have happened. So מכאן שפותחין בנולד, mican sheposchin b'nolad, so
you see you can open up with the fact that something that
occurred afterwards that wasn't able to be expected and use that as
a basis to undo the vow. רבנן, Rabanan, and the rabbis would
say back, מאי טעמייהו? mai ta'amayhu? What's their reasoning? Excuse me, what's
the reasoning of the rabbis? קסברי הנהו מי מיתי? kasvari hanhu mi
meisi? Who said they died? ואמר רבי יוחנן... ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan... That's
a פשט, peshat,
but who says that's true? והאמר רבי יוחנן...
ve'ha amar Rabbi Yochanan...
That's not how you read the פסוק. pasuk. Oh come on, that's
not how you read the פסוק. pasuk. That's how you read a
פסוק? pasuk? Okay, ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, that's like the
joke, oh that's how a ספרדי Sefardi reads the רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay,
ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, didn't רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי, mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, כל מקום
שנאמר נצים ונצבים kol makom shene'emar nitzim v'nitzavim when it says that
they were standing or, you know, or fighting or standing,
אינם אלא דתן ואבירם. einam ela Dathan v'Aviram. So it starts with
the fact that משה Moshe saw שני אנשים עברים נצים, shnei anashim
Ivrim nitzim, ויאמר לרשע למה תכה רעך, vayo'mer larasha lama sakeh re'echa,
right, ויאמר מי שמך לאיש שר ושופט עלינו. vayo'mer mi samcha l'ish
sar v'shofet aleinu. So משה Moshe runs away because of these two.
Hebrews that were ניצים Nitzim fighting. And then later it says, after
he returns to מצרים Mitzrayim and he has problems with פרעה, Paroh,
that he's encountered that they were ניצבים לקראתם בצאתם מפרעה, Nitzavim likratam
betzeitam mei-Paroh, right? At the end of the people that were standing
to meet them and saying, who, why did you come? You've only
caused us problems,
et cetera. So חז"ל say, it's a similar type of a response,
right? Completely sort of challenging משה's Moshe's authority. Here he is coming
to do good, who needs you, and so on. It's a very
similar response. There are similar words, ניצים Nitzim and ניצבים. Nitzavim.
And we're looking for who's the bad guy? Where are some good
bad guys to find? Well, דתן Dasan and אבירם Aviram by קורח
Korach it says, יצאו ניצבים. yatzu nitzavim. So let's just say that
they're all the same person. Okay, so if they're all the same
person, then it's not true כי מתו כל האנשים המבקשים את נפשך.
ki meisu kol ha'anashim ham'vakshim es nafshecha. Of course, the funny thing
is, since when are the people that were מבקשים את נפשך m'vakshim
es nafshecha דתן Dasan and אבירם? Aviram? I would have thought it
was פרעה, Paroh, right? All right, somehow though, that's how we're reading
it, okay?
So somehow it was דתן Dasan and
אבירם Aviram who informed on him. Informed on him, right, or the
word got to him, מפרעה, mi-Paroh, but ultimately it was פרעה Paroh
who wanted to kill him. So that's also, right, so somehow it's
like, well, since the people that are making trouble and talking to
whatever, they're not there, so maybe פרעה Paroh also would have moved
on or something. I don't know. But one would have more imagined
that it would have had to do with the fact that it
says that the king of מצרים Mitzrayim died, right? That would have
probably been a little more פשט. pshat.
Okay, anyway, here's
the claim, by claiming that the people, the only people interested or
the source of the whole problem remains דתן Dasan and אבירם, Aviram,
and דתן Dasan and אבירם Aviram are still alive, based, right, and
they were the people that were starting this, we could say it
doesn't literally mean that anybody died. That's not the point. אמר ריש
לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, so what does it mean? So that they
died? שירדו מנכסיהם, She-yardu minichseihem,
that they became poor, so they lost their influence. And presumably becoming
poor is something that happens, and it's akin to
it's akin to dying.
It's akin to dying on the one hand and the other hand,
it's not a total נוולד nolad because it's something that you could
have expected might have happened that they might have lost their influence.
You know it says a guy can like make a gift except
for himself, you
know it just says that. That's true. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כל אדם שאין לו בנים חשוב כמת.
kol adam she-ein lo banim chashuv k'meis. Anybody who does not have
children is like they are dead. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, הבה לי בנים ואם
אין מתה אנכי, hava li banim v'im ayin meisa anochi, and if
give me sons or children and if not I'll be I am
dead. ותניא, V'tanya, right, ארבעה חשובים כמת. arba'ah chashuvin k'meis. There are
four that are considered like dead. עני ומצורע וסומא ומי שאין לו
בנים. Ani u'metzora v'suma u'mi she-ein lo banim. Somebody who's poor, somebody
who's leprous, somebody
who's blind, and somebody who has no children. עני דכתיב כי מתו
כל האנשים, Ani de-chtiv ki meisu kol ha'anashim, all the people died
and they didn't die as we just said. A little circular because
it never says they became poor, but that's how we're reading it.
מצורע דכתיב אל נא תהי כמת, Metzora de-chtiv al na sehi k'meis,
let her not be like dead. Now that might have to do
with the fact that the very physical affliction turns the person like
white and pale as if a person had become had become dead.
But of course what you could also understand is, right, if you're
poor, if you're poor, you're like at the margins of society, if
you have no influence, nobody, you're not treated with honor or respect
or so on, and if you're מצורע, metzora, you're cast out of
society, right? So somebody who's totally cast out of society, there's a
type of a
communal death that occurs in terms of
that. וסומא דכתיב במחשכים הושיבני כמתי עולם. V'suma de-chtiv b'machshakim hoshivani k'meisei
olam. Look at that, very appropriate to just yesterday. God made me
dwell in darkness like the dead. So if you're living in darkness,
right, it's that's what we sort of see, the dead go into
the dark underworld, the netherworld, and so on. And also, especially in
the past, the ability of a blind person to navigate society. Of
course, there are other things that the גמרא, it's
interesting others it seems to have been very much...
Right, it is interesting if you try to translate this practically, why
is the גמרא identifying סומא suma more than let's say, I don't
know, the חרש cheireish in this or the somebody who can't speak
and can't hear, which has obviously halachically is considered
even more unable to interact with larger society, not considered a בר
דעת, bar da'as, bracketing for a moment obviously how that status has
changed, halachically and so on and how that was partly a reality
about how society treated such people. I'm not sort of condoning that,
but I'm still saying it's interesting that the גמרא identifies the blind
person as opposed to people with other types of disabilities and so
on that might have made it even more challenging for them. Maybe
specifically it is the פסוק pasuk and it is that sense of
being in darkness and that sense that death and darkness and so
on are associated. ומי שאין לו בנים דכתיב הבה לי בנים ואם
אין מתה אנכי, U'mi she-ein lo banim de-chtiv hava li banim v'im
ayin meisa anochi, and that clearly could be because of that sense
of continuity, a person lives on through their children, they pass away
from the world but their children are their continuity, and what that
sense when a
person doesn't have that. As I quoted this before, Woody Allen once
said, he said... I don't want to become immortal through my work.
I want to become immortal through not dying. Right? So anyway, alright,
so that ties up this idea of the four like a dead
and that somehow explains this because we say that מיתה, misa, becoming
poor, is not so much of a נולד nolad as as the
idea of dying. Alright, let's I guess read. What time is it?
Oh, look at that! We started, we're even a little ahead. Let's
read a little bit further. תניא, Tanya, maybe we'll even get to
the משנה. What are we going to do if we're so
ahead?
Okay, המודר הנאה מחבירו. Hamudar hana'ah me-chavero. What?
Yom Kippur is coming up. Right, yeah, okay, there we go. המודר
הנאה מחבירו Hamudar hana'ah me-chavero אין מתירין לו אלא בפניו. ein matirin
lo ella be-fanav. Somebody takes a vow. You know what? Actually, this
is like a nice juicy סוגיא, sugya, I don't want to rush
through it, so let's actually we'll just end here, we won't get
ahead, and we'll pick up here tomorrow. Okay. Rabbi.